בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. We're a little behind. Today's דף Daf
should be צ"ד, Tzadik Daled, צ"ד, Tzadik Daled, but we start at
the bottom of צ"ג עמוד א' Tzadik Gimmel Amud Aleph and we
pick up with the whole story about how these two false prophets
were who are using their false prophecy to basically take advantage of
these women. That doesn't sound like anything in the news these days.
Anyway,
נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar basically threw them into the fire test them like חנניה,
Hananiah, מישאל Mishael and עזריה. Azariah. They said we need a third
person so they got יהושע כהן גדול. Yehoshua Kohen Gadol. And it
says we pick up I guess from it
says אמר להון. Amar Lehon.
So one, two, three, four, five, about ten lines from the bottom
going a little back. אמר להון, Amar Lehon, he said to them,
בחרו לכון מן דבעיתו. Bechiru Lechon Man Debe'isu. Fine, pick a third
guy. אדייכו. Adaichehu. אמר יהושע כהן גדול. Amar Yehoshua Kohen Gadol. Line
starts with כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
סברי, Savri, they figured, ליתי יהושע דנפיש זכותיה. Leisye Yehoshua De-nevitz d'zechusei.
All right, we know we're false prophets, but let יהושע Yehoshua come,
he's has a lot of merit and his merit will protect us.
ומגן עלן, U-magen Alan, it'll protect us. אחסיוהו, Achasyuhu, so they brought,
so they brought him. שדיוהו, Shadyuhu, they threw him into the fire.
אינהו איקלו, Innu Iklu, they got burned. יהושע כהן גדול Yehoshua Kohen
Gadol איחרכו, Ichrachu, he his he got scarred he what a charred,
singed, singed. מאני, Manei, his his his garments got singed. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
ויראני את יהושע הכהן הגדול עומד לפני מלאך ה' Vayar'eini es Yehoshua
Ha-kohen Ha-gadol Omeid lifnei malach Hashem וכתיב u-ksiv ויאמר ה' אל השטן
יגער ה' בך השטן, Vayomer Hashem el hasatan yig'ar Hashem becha hasatan,
you know, anyway, and it says and
anyway
we're going to get to the fact that his garments, you know,
הלא זה אוד מצל מאש. Halo zeh ud mutzal me-eish. He is
a poker that's been saved from the fire. So that with that's
what it's referring to. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ידענא דצדיקא את. yadanah
d'tzadikkah at. So נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar says, look, I know they were false
prophets and I know you're a righteous person. אלא מאי טעמא אהניא
בך פורתא נורא? Ela mai ta'amah ahanya becha purtza nura? So and
חנניה, מישאל ועזריה Chananya Mishael vaAzarya. לא אהניא בהו כלל. lo ahanya
behu klal. Why is it that the fire a little bit affected
you and it didn't affect חנניה, Hananiah, מישאל Mishael and עזריה Azariah
at all? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, אינהו
תלתא הוו ואנא חד. innu tlatah havau va-ana chad. They were three,
I was only one. I mean, you know, so. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, ואברהם יחיד הוה? ve-Avraham yachid havah? But אברהם Avraham was one
and he was thrown into the fire, you know, and he got
saved according to the whole מדרש. Midrash. התם לא הוו רשעים בהדיה.
Hasam lo hava resha'im ba-adei. Ah yeah, but he didn't have wicked
people with him. ולא איתיהיב רשותא לנורא. Ve-lo is-yehav reshusa l'nura. And
the fire wasn't given permission to have dominion over, you know, the
fire was totally off limits. הכא הוו רשעים בהדיה. Hacha hava resha'im
ba-adei. Here there were wicked people with me. ואיתיהיב רשותא לנורא. Ve-is-yehav
reshusa l'nura. And the fire had permission and therefore it burned them
and since it burned them and the fire was actually burning I
got a little bit affected.
היינו דאמרי אינשי. Hainu d'amri inshi. That's what people say. תרי אודי
יבשי וחד רטיבא. Trei udi yaveshi ve-chad rativa. If you have two
like embers like a stick, logs, that are, אוד ud is usually
like a poker, but I think here it means like two logs,
you know, and you know the severe or trying to start a
fire. You have some wet and some dry. So if you have
two that are dry and one is wet, so because the dry
ones catch fire and they get the fire going, so therefore אוכדן
יבשי לרטיבא. okdin yaveshi le-rativa. The dry ones allow the even the
wet one to catch, you know, to catch fire. Okay, so מאי
טעמא איענש? mai ta'ama i'aneshu? The גמרא Gemara says that's all very
nice as an answer to נבוכדנצר. Nebuchadnezzar. But you know, he would
not have even had his garments singed if there was not something
he had done that was deserving of it.
Despite the fact that there were רשעים.
resha'im. Right. So the גמרא Gemara still says we still need a
real reason why he got punished. So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Papa, שהיו בניו נושאים נשים שאינן הגונות לכהונה. she-hayu banav nosim nashim
she-einam hagunos li-khunah. Because his wives would marry children, excuse me, his
children married wives that they shouldn't have married based on their status
as כהנים. Kohanim. Maybe not actually באיסור, be-issur, but it was not
fit for them. Okay, so that's why a little bit of singe,
a little like it a little dirtied his garment. A little bit
of a impinged on the status of כהונה. kehunah. ולא מיחה בהן.
Ve-lo michei ba-hen. And he was did not
protest. שנאמר Shene'emar ויהושע היה לבוש בגדים צואים. ve-Yehoshua hayah lavush begadim
tzo'im. Soiled garments. So it's like something external to him, but it's
still like attached to him. Okay, וכי דרכו של יהושע ללבוש בגדים
צואים? ve-khi darkei de-Yehoshua l'milbash begadim tzo'im? Would he deal actually soiled
garment, wear it? אלא מלמד שהיו בניו נושאים נשים שאינן הגונות לכהונה.
Ela melamed she-hayu banav nosim nashim she-einam hagunos li-khunah. He didn't protest
and somehow a little bit of that splattered back on him. Okay,
אמר רבי תנחום, Amar Rabbi Tanchum, דרש בר קפרא בציפורי, darash Bar
Kappara b'Tzippori, מאי דכתיב? mai de-ksiv? What's meant by the verse?
שש שעורים האלה נתן לי. Sheish se'orim ha-eileh nasan li. By רות
Ruth and בועז, Boaz, yes, he gave me these six barleys. So
what what does it mean six barleys? מאי שש שעורים? Mai sheish
se'orim? אילימא שש שעורים ממש? Ileima sheish se'orim mamash? Just like six
kernels of barley. וכי דרכו של בועז ליתן מתנה שש שעורים? Ve-khi
darkah de-Boaz litten mattanah sheish se'orim? That's a gift? Six kernels of
barley? So אלא שש סאה? ela sheish se'ah? You'll say it's six
סאה? se'ah? Six huge boxes of barley. וכי דרכה של אשה ליטול
שש סאה? Ve-khi darkah de-ishah litol sheish se'ah? Can she carry that
amount? Of course רש"י Rashi says what about a smaller amount? All
right, so רש"י Rashi says well, you know, but they were in
the גורן, goren, they were in the threshing floor, so you don't
use small amounts, you only have large... I don't know what to
tell you. Anyway, אלא רמז רמז לה. ela remez ramaz lah. So
it was six little kernels of barley and he was giving her
a symbol, she a hint,
שעתידים ששה בנים לצאת ממנה. she-atidim shishah banim latzeis mimmenah. She would
have six descendants, six literally six children, שמתברכין בשש שש ברכות. she-mishborchin
be-sheish sheish brachot. So there's a double six. Six children and each
one of the six children gets six blessings. אלו הן, Eilu hein,
these are the six children. דוד ומשיח, David u-Mashiach, דניאל, Daniel, חנניה,
Hananiah, מישאל, Mishael ועזריה. ve-Azariah So we know דוד David was her,
you know, descendant and משיח Mashiach is בן דוד, Ben David, and
דניאל, Daniel, חנניה, Chananya, מישאל, Mishael, and עזריה Azarya we are saying
that they were all, you know, of descendant of the Davidic household
or certainly from the tribe of יהודה, Yehuda, but according to this
descendant of the Davidic household. Okay דוד, David, now we're going to
see, so that's six. Now we're going to see how each one
has six blessings. דוד David דכתיב, de-chtiv, ויען אחד מהנערים ויאמר הנה
ראיתי בן לישי בית הלחמי, va-ya'an echad m'ha-ne'arim va-yomer, hinei ra'iti ben
l'Yishai Beit ha-Lachmi, one of the lads and we'll see that that's
going to be דואג, Doeg, said to שאול, Shaul, I've seen the
child, one of the children of ישי, Yishai, and he knows the
following: יודע נגן yode'a nagen one, וגיבור v'gibor he's valorous, וגיבור חיל
v'gibor chayil excuse me, ואיש מלחמה v'ish milchama a man of war,
ונבון u-nevon understanding ונבון דבר u-nevon davar four, ואיש תואר v'ish to'ar
and handsome, וה' עמו v'Hashem imo six. Now, ואמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, v'amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav, כל הפסוק הזה לא אמרו דואג
אלא בלשון הרע. kol ha-pasuk hazeh lo amaro Doeg ela b'lashon hara.
There's quite interesting. What do you mean? That's six praises, these are
the six blessings. So it's not that he said bad things, but
he said it בלשון הרע. bi-l'shon hara. He said it with evil
intent. He said it in order as רש"י Rashi says to get
שאול Shaul jealous of דוד. David. Okay, so you could say a
praise and you're saying it with an evil tongue, okay, even though
the content isn't evil.
יודע נגן, yode'a nagen, now here's how he was getting, now but
it's all praises, it's praises said בלשון הרע. bi-l'shon hara. And here's
how he was, here's what he was saying. יודע נגן, yode'a nagen,
שיודע, she-yode'a, now it's not just סתם stam he knows how to
play a musical instrument, that's not going to get שאול Shaul jealous.
No, שיודע לשאול, she-yode'a lish'ol, he knows how to ask good questions
in learning. גיבור, Gibor, valorous, שיודע להשיב, she-yode'a l'hashiv, he knows not
only how to ask questions, he knows how to give answers. That
requires, it's always, you can always ask a
question. איש מלחמה, ish milchama, man of war, שיודע לישא וליתן במלחמתה
של תורה. she-yode'a lisa u-litein b'milchamta shel Torah. He knows how to
actually fight the battles of תורה, Torah, give and take, right? Not
just to response, somebody pushes back, there's the give and the take.
Now it just reverses the order here if you go in terms
of the פסוק. pasuk. So when there's a parenthesis and an asterisk,
it doesn't mean take it out, it means replace what's taken out
in the parenthesis with what's on the side. So if you look
at the side, it's ונבון דבר, u-nevon davar, שמבין דבר מתוך דבר,
she-mevin davar mitoch davar, right? He's able to infer things, intuit things.
That's what a נבון navon is. Right, I know, I understand. איש
תואר, Ish to'ar, a man of of good looks, שמראה פנים בהלכה.
she-mareh panim ba-halacha. He's able to actually show the right הלכה, halacha,
show how to how to act. וה' עמו, v'Hashem imo, שהלכה כמותו
בכל מקום. she-halacha k'moto b'chol makom. And we actually always will פוסקין
paskin like דוד. David. Okay, so obviously it's so fascinating how חז"ל
Chazal are reading it through their lens. The way you praise somebody,
he says he's a good תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and the הלכה
halacha is like him.
הלכה כמותו, Halacha k'moto, you know, that he's, we understand what happens
to him later, but you know we retroject that back, like oh
he's always evil and he always meant to be evil and then
it turned into something that was good. Right, right, right.
בכולהו אמר להו, B'chulu amar lehu, when all these praises when these
were being said to שאול, Shaul, he said אפס, efes, יונתן בני
כמהו, Yonatan b'ni kamohu, meh, יונתן Yonatan my son is just as
good as him. כיון דאמר ליה Keivan de-amar lei וה' עמו, v'Hashem
imo, when God is with him, במילתא דבדידיה נמי לא הוה ביה,
bi-milta d'bidida nami lo hava bei, something that even he didn't have.
Now of course you might think it means, you know, of course
שאול Shaul was taken by this, you know, by this evil spirit
or whatever, you know, probably, you know, interesting ways to sort of
medicalize that, right, you know, in terms of his mental state. But
anyway, and you know, and but but here it's reading it through
this lens of the איש ish or the הלכה כמותו. halacha k'moto.
So if הלכה כמותו בכל מקום, halacha k'moto b'chol makom, the הלכה
halacha can only be like one opinion. Okay,
חלש דעתיה. chalash da'atei. So then שאול Shaul became like despaired. Okay,
ואיקנא ביה ואיקנא ביה, v'itne bei b'itne bei,
and he became jealous of דוד, David, which was was according to
the גמרא Gemara the goal here. דבשאול כתיב, De-v'Shaul ketiv, by שאול
Shaul it says ובכל אשר יפנה ירשיע, u-v'chol asher yifneh yarshia, wherever
he would turn he would do evil. Now not so הלכה halacha
not פוסקין paskin like somebody doesn't mean ירשיע, yarshia, but anyway here
it's just contrasting it. ובדוד כתיב, U-v'David ketiv, ובכל אשר יפנה יצליח.
u-v'chol asher yifneh yatzliach. Okay, fine. Now of course if you look
at the side it says לא מקרא במקרא לשון זה. lo mikra
b'mikra lashon zeh. Okay, that's nice to quote that פסוק, pasuk, but
it doesn't actually say that פסוק pasuk anywhere. It's nice to make
it as a contrast to שאול. Shaul. ולא צריך לומר V'lo tzarich
lomar לכל דרכיו משכיל. l'chol drachav maskil. Alright, it's interesting. It says
this by שאול Shaul and the opposite by דוד. David. Except they
didn't say it by דוד, David, but okay. It should have said
it by דוד. David. Okay, anyway.
ומנלן דדואג הוה, U-minan de-Doeg hava, now how do we know that
the person saying this was דואג Doeg and he was trying to
get שאול Shaul jealous? כתיב הכא Ketiv hacha ויען אחד מהנערים, va-ya'an
echad m'ha-ne'arim, one of the lads. מיוחס שבנערים, Meyuchas she-ba-ne'arim, one of
the choice ones. דכתיב התם De-ketiv hatam ושם איש מעבדי שאול ביום
ההוא נעצר לפני ה', v'sham ish me-avdei Shaul bayom ha-hu ne'etzar lifnei
Hashem, there's a person there from the servants of שאול, Shaul, ושמו
דואג האדומי אביר הרועים, u-shmo Doeg ha-Edomi avir ha-ro'im, the strong one
of the shepherds, but I mean like the choice of שאול'ס Shaul's
servants or of שאול'ס, Shaul's, you know, attendants, אשר לשאול. asher l'Shaul.
Okay fine. So those are the six of דוד. David. משיח, Mashiach,
the משיח, Mashiach, דכתיב de-chtiv ונחה עליו רוח ה', v'nachu alav ruach
Hashem, the spirit of God one, רוח חכמה ruach chochma two, ובינה
u-vina three, רוח עצה ruach eitzah four, וגבורה u-gevura five, רוח דעת
ויראת ה'. ruach da'at v'yirat Hashem. Oh okay I miscounted. Maybe רוח
ה' ruach Hashem is the כותרת. koteret. So it's רוח חכמה ruach
chochma one, ובינה u-vina two, רוח עצה ruach eitzah three, וגבורה u-gevura
four, רוח דעת ruach da'at understanding, ויראת ה' v'yirat Hashem is six.
Okay,
וכתיב v'chtiv והריחו ביראת ה'. v'haricho b'yirat Hashem. I, you know, I'm
sort of losing count, is that supposed to be seven? or is
that, did I miscount a little bit?
They have a wordplay like with the רוח ruach and the ריח.
reiach.
Right, well that I know, but the question is are you counting
והריחו vaharicho as number seven or and were we supposed to have
combined something before, like דעת ויראת השם da'at veyirat Hashem is one?
Whatever it is, somewhere you get six. There's more than six, but
somehow you conflate them, you get six. Okay, now as Micha properly
said, oh, Rashi actually takes out the word וכתיב, ukhtiv, because Rashi
is bothered by the same thing. If when you end the פסוק
pasuk יראת השם, yirat Hashem, period, you've got six, period. Now we're
done with counting. Now moving on to a different point, let's look
at this פסוק pasuk by משיח. Mashiach. And Micha's correct because it
speaks about רוח, ruach, רוח, ruach, רוח. ruach. It's the tie-in to
והריחו ביראת השם, vaharicho beyirat Hashem, he will smell with the fear
of God. Okay, so that's not being counted in the number. Okay,
so now we're going to talk a little bit about that by
משיח. Mashiach. יראת השם yirat Hashem anyway. I understand, so it could
be the same version of the same. אמר רב אלכסנדרי, Amar Rav
Alexandri, מלמד שהטעינו מצוות ויסורין כריחיים. melamed shehitino mitzvot veyissurin kerei chayim.
You know, משיח Mashiach will be laid down with, it's interesting, מצוות,
mitzvot, but also with afflictions. Okay, you know, I mean that's the
whole thing, the afflicted servant. Right, I mean there are פסוקים psukim
about that. I mean we think about this as a Christian idea,
but the Christians are taking it from a פסוק pasuk in ישעיהו
Yeshayahu that talks about, you know, עני ורוכב על החמור, ani verochev
al hachamor, right, and the afflicted servant and so on. So this
is talking, you know, maybe presumably מלחמת גוג ומגוג. milchemet Gog uMagog.
It's not all going to be easy for him initially. So the
word והריחו, vaharicho, to smell, is ביראת השם, beyirat Hashem, so he'll
do מצוות, mitzvot, but he'll be weighed down like a millstone. Okay,
he'll be challenged for him. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so רבא Rava
says more within the literal meaning of the פסוק, pasuk, דמורח ודאין.
demorach vedayin. He can smell out truth. He can smell out like
something smells fishy here. Like he can, just by smelling, he'll be
able to tell if somebody is telling the truth or lying. דכתיב,
Dechtiv, it says, ולא למראה עיניו ישפוט ולא למשמע אזניו יוכיח. velo
lemareh einav yishpot velo lemishma oznav yochiach. Right, he won't be judged
just based on what he can see externally. ושפט בצדק דלים. Veshafat
betzedek dalim. And but he'll judge righteously. How will he judge righteously
if you won't do it based on what he sees? והוכיח במישור
לענוי ארץ. Vehochiach bemishor leanvei aretz. So he'll do it because he'll
have this ability to smell out the truth. בר כוזיבא Bar Koziba
מלך תרתין שנין. malach tartin shanin. Now בר כוזיבא Bar Koziba was
בר כוכבא, Bar Kochba, but of course there's a play on words,
right? בר כוכבא Bar Kochba is like the star and כוזיבא Koziba
is like כזב kazav is like false, right, because he proved to
be a false משיח, Mashiach, okay. So בר כוזיבא Bar Koziba might
have actually been his name. Okay. What was he interesting about? Did
anyone believe him?
That's a good question too, right, yeah, but right. So anyway, so
בר כוזיבא Bar Koziba מלך תרתין שנין. malach tartin shanin. He was
a king for two years, he had two years, I mean not
king, but whatever, anyway, he was leading this rebellion for two
years. ופלגא, Ufalga, two and a half years. אמר להו לרבנן אנא
משיח. Amar lehu lerabbanan ana Mashiach. So according to the גמרא, Gemara,
he said that he was the משיח. Mashiach. אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
במשיח כתיב. beMashiach ktiv. So they said, wait a minute, by the
משיח Mashiach it says, דמורח ודאין, demorach vedayin, you can smell out
he could smell out the truth. נחזי אנן אי מורח ודאין. Nechezi
anan i morach vedayin. Let's see if you can do that.
כיון דחזיוהו, Keivan dechazyuhu, they saw him, דלא מורח ודאין, delo morach
vedayin, he couldn't smell out the truth. קטלוהו, Katluhu, they killed him.
Now, of course, the question is why did they kill him? What
did he, I mean, okay, he's not the משיח, Mashiach, and they
killed him? Or the Romans killed him? So that's one question. The
other question is רמב"ם, Rambam, if you remember I mentioned to you
before that רמב"ם Rambam has a big point that משיח Mashiach doesn't
have to do any miracles. So רמב"ם Rambam basically says משיח Mashiach
doesn't have to do any miracles. So he says, and then רמב"ם
Rambam says, how did they know בר כוכבא Bar Kochba wasn't the
משיח? Mashiach? So according to, he says different than the גמרא. Gemara.
He says they knew בר כוכבא Bar Kochba wasn't the משיח Mashiach
because he died and he did not fulfill the promises that משיח
Mashiach was supposed to fulfill. Now for רמב"ם, Rambam, he says this
at the end of הלכות מלכים Hilchot Melachim and it's a very
edited, censored text because there's also the whole anti-Christian polemic going on
there and what he also is saying implicitly is that and therefore
Jesus wasn't the משיח Mashiach because Jesus also died. Okay. But anyway,
but that's what רמב"ם Rambam says. So ראב"ד Ra'avad says, what do
you mean? That's not how they knew he wasn't the משיח. Mashiach.
He knew he wasn't the משיח Mashiach because he didn't smell out
truth. And he quotes this גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So then people say,
well, maybe the רמב"ם Rambam disagreed with this גמרא. Gemara. Maybe he
found a different גמרא, Gemara, ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, who knows? Whatever. They try
to support, you know, to explain how the רמב"ם Rambam is able
to take his שיטה shitah and sort of bracket the גמרות Gemorot
that don't work with it. But the other interesting thing is that
some of the נושאי כלים nosei kelim said, what do you, anyway,
it doesn't really mean that the rabbis killed him. Why would the
rabbis have killed him? Even according to this גמרא, Gemara, maybe it
means that they didn't protect him when the Romans tried to kill
him. Like they try to re-read this גמרא Gemara to make
it consistent with history. And B, why would they kill him? Although
some want to say that the claim maybe that you're משיח Mashiach
is essentially a type of a נביא שקר. navi sheker. Although you're
not saying you're a נביא, navi, you're just saying you're the משיח.
Mashiach. Right, it's a very interesting question. Right, we have had false
messiahs. What type of a sin is it to claim you're the
false messiah? Anyway, so moving on.
You're saying as no one's really saying this is under pain of
death.
Some do. Some actually try to say that it's similar to being
like a false prophet. But others, even though they defend this, even
though they sort of embrace this גמרא Gemara against רמב"ם Rambam and
say משיח Mashiach has to be able to have this magical or
whatever divine ability, but they say it doesn't mean literally the rabbis
killed him.
Just to say that this was the test that was given to
him.
Right. Well, but that’s also interesting, right? Because it does it is
closer to רמב"ם Rambam that right that’s worth pointing out too, that
it’s closer to רמב"ם Rambam that it’s not like you have to
make an addition, do totally miraculous things. You have to transform the
nature of reality, right? That the whole test is a, okay, it’s
still a supernatural ability, but it’s a limited one. So
even, so it’s interesting that that, you’re right, that like that suffices.
Okay. All right.
Now, so that’s number two. Now, the next four people that were
given these six blessings each was Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah, דכתיב
בהו, dechtiv behu, that’s four. אשר אין בהם כל מום, asher ein
bahem kol mum, it’s right at the beginning of the Daniel where
it talks about the people that were taken in exile from Judea,
amongst them Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael and Azariah. So it says these lads
of Judea that had no blemish one.
What does the אלף aleph do?
I don’t know, it’s I think it’s just a spelling thing, it’s
a later book, Daniel. Okay. וטובי מראה, vetovei mareh, of good visage
appearance, ומשכילים בכל חכמה, umaskilim bechol chochmah, wise, יודעי דעת, yodei da'as,
knowledgeable four, ומביני מדע, umevinei mada, understanding five, ואשר כח בהם לעמוד
בהיכל המלך, va'asher koach bahem la'amod beheichal hamelech, they had
the ability to stand in the king’s court. So, so וללמדם ספר
ולשון כשדים ulelamdam sefer uleshon kasdim
and to teach them books and the language of the Chaldeans. I
don’t know why that doesn’t count as seven and eight. Okay. מאי
אשר אין בהם כל מום, mai asher ein bahem kol mum, what
does it mean they have no blemish? אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא,
amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina, אפילו כריבדא דכוסילתא לא הוי בהו. afilu
karivda dechusilta lo havai behu. They didn’t even have the puncture that
you make with the blood-letting vessel, like they never even needed to
have their blood let, so they didn’t even have the puncture in
their skin you would make by one of those things. ואשר כח
בהם לעמוד בהיכל המלך, va'asher koach bahem la'amod beheichal hamelech, they had
the ability to stand in the king’s court. אמר רבי חמא בר
חנינא, amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina, מלמד שהיו אונסין את עצמן מן
השחוק ומן השיחה ומן השינה, melamed shehayu onsin es atzman min haschok
umin hasicha umin hasheina, ומעמידין על עצמן בשעה שנצרכין לנקביהם מפני אימת
מלכות. uma'amidin al atzman besha'ah shenitzrachin lenekveihem mipnei eimas malchus. They would
stand in the king’s court for like hours on end, right, what
are you supposed to, you can’t take a bathroom break when you’re
standing in the king’s, in the king’s court. So they had to
be able to not, A, not crack any jokes, not do anything
distracting, just stand like you ever see those guys by like, what
is it by in Westminster, not Westminster Abbey, where is it where
they do the whole guard thing? Buckingham Palace! Right, they’re like totally
like whatever. Okay, so they don’t, they don’t nod off, they don’t
kid around, they can’t even go to the bathroom. Okay. And they
have to just stand.
I don’t, did
you say anything about how? I understand, but I’m ויהיו בהם מבני
יהודה דניאל חנניה מישאל ועזריה. vayihyu bahem mibnei Yehuda Daniel Chanania Mishael
va'Azaria.
So in this פסוק pasuk it says amongst those that were taken
in captivity that was described with these blessings, there was Daniel, Hananiah,
Mishael, and Azariah. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, כולם מבני יהודה
הן. kulam mibnei Yehuda hen. They were all from the descendants of
Judah and that’s the end of this idea that they were all
descendants of Ruth. Okay. ורבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר, veRabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar,
he disagrees with this idea and he says דניאל מבני יהודה. Daniel
mibnei Yehuda. No, Daniel was מבני יהודה. mibnei Yehuda. חנניה מישאל ועזריה
משאר שבטים. Chanania Mishael va'Azaria mishar shevatim. They were from the other
tribes. Okay. ומבניך אשר יצאו ממך אשר תוליד יקחו והיו סריסים בהיכל
מלך בבל. umibanecha asher yetzu mimecha asher tolid yikachu vehayu sarisim beheichal
melech Bavel. This is the prophecy about again, I forget who this
was said to. Hezekiah?
Yeah, fine, Hezekiah. Right. Anyway, this is the prophecy about,
this is given to one of the מלכי יהודה, malchei Yehuda, I
forget which one, but anyway he says, but, but the prophecy is
that your children, it might be צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, your children who will
come out of your loins, that you will give birth to, they
will be taken in captivity and they will become eunuchs in the
king’s court, בבל, Bavel, בהיכל מלך בבל. beheichal melech Bavel. מאי סריסים,
mai sarisim, what does it mean eunuchs? רב אמר סריסים ממש. Rav
amar sarisim mamash. Yeah, I mean, that’s what, that’s what it says.
That’s what happened. ורבי חנינא אמר שנסתרסה עבודה זרה בימיהם. veRabbi Chanina
amar shenistarsha avodah zarah beymeihem. So in the middle of this curse
is as like a praise and it doesn’t mean they’ll be eunuchs,
it means that עבודה זרה avodah zarah will be eunuchized, I don’t
know, I just made up that verb, anyway, in their days, because
the whole sort of things that happen with נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and Daniel
and the
ways in which Chanania, Mishael,
Azariah were proven correct and like the whole, anyway, okay. I mean,
they say like a lot of times סריס המלך saris hamelech doesn’t
necessarily mean eunuchs. It just means what?
It just
means,
I understand, but no, why, I don’t know.
I don’t know, because when does it not mean eunuch? Okay.
If you say סריס המלך saris hamelech in Esther, it means eunuchs?
Yeah, yeah, totally. That’s what they did. The people that worked in
the king’s court, they didn’t want them tempted by the king’s harem
or whatever. So they, none of those were, but they, I don’t
know.
I don’t, it could be just like to incapacitate somebody, right? To
make somebody not able to,
as
opposed to through surgically doing it? It could be used metaphorically, I
assume it could. Well, that’s how it’s being used here, except not
about them, about the idolatry because all the stories there in ספר
דניאל Sefer Daniel was how the idolatry was proven false and so
on. Anyway, okay. בשלמא למאן דאמר שנסתרסה עבודה זרה בימיהם היינו דכתיב
וחבל לא איתי בהון. bishlama leman damar shenistarsha avodah zarah beymeihem hainu
dechsiv vechaval lo isai behon.
There was no wound in them. They, they were like before, they
also didn’t have a מום. mum. So you don’t want to say
that they actually were eunuchized, I don’t know, whatever, there’s got to
be another word for that, there is a word, what is it?
To castrated? Well, castrated. אלא למאן דאמר סריסים ממש, ela leman damar
sarisim mamash,
literal, literally means they were eunuchs and castrated, מאי וחבל לא איתי
בהון, mai vechaval lo isai behon, they didn’t have any wound? חבל
דנורא. chavala denura.
No, no, no. when they were thrown into the fire, the fire
didn't have any have any you know because that was the context
that was when they were thrown in the fire the fire didn't
actually affect them. It doesn't mean that they didn't have any blemish
at all. Okay and by the way the reason they didn't have
from the earlier pasuk where it says they didn't have any מום
mum was that's when they were taken into captivity. Right? When they
were taken into captivity they didn't have any מום mum but then
they would have been castrated. So you can't ask from the verse
that says they didn't have a מום mum but here later on
after they've been now in Nevuchadnezzar's court it says they didn't have
any blemish or they didn't have any wound but it says that
wound just means that they weren't affected by the fire. Okay והכתיב
vehaksiv but doesn't it say וריח נור לא עדת בהון vereyach nur
lo adas bahon ולא
חבלה velo chavala so doesn't it say but the fire did not
you know did not impact them? So the double language the fire
didn't impact them and there wasn't any wound presumably means wound even
beyond the fire. So the Gemara says no לא חבלה ולא ריחא.
lo chavala velo reicha. No
the double language is just to say A they didn't have any
fire damage and B they didn't have any smoke damage. Okay they
were completely unaffected. Okay but it does not mean that they weren't
castrated. בשלמא למאן דאמר bishlama leman deamar it's good according to the
one who says שנסתרסה עבודה זרה בימיהם shenistarsa avoda zara bimeihem היינו
דכתיב hainu dechsiv כה אמר השם לסריסים אשר ישמרו את שבתותי koh
amar Hashem lasarisim asher yishmeru es shabsosai to those eunuchs who will
keep my Sabbath. Now of course there what's bizarre the פשט pshat
of there is what do you mean they're saying that they're saying
that we won't have children and God says don't worry you know
you'll know you know יד ושם yad vashem and you know you'll
have fame you know whatever this even without biological descendants you know
but the גמרא gemara is reading it that the פסוקים psukim would
not be highlighting the fact that they were סריסים sarisim if they
were literal סריסים sarisim right? So therefore if it's highlighting it it
only makes sense if we're talking about the fact that they merit
this thing because עבודה זרה avoda zara was destroyed or not destroyed
but whatever castrated in their days. So אלא למאן דאמר סריסים ממש
ela leman deamar sarisim mamash
משום דגנותא דצדיקי mishum dignuso detzadikei
the פסוקים psukim would be highlighting the bad thing about these righteous
persons?
So it says no הא והא הוו בהו ha veha havu behu
fine so according to that approach it's not just that they were
that they were castrated it's also שנסתרסה עבודה זרה בימיהם. shenistarsa avoda
zara bimeihem. So when the pasuk highlights the fact that they were
סריסים sarisim it's talking about the fact that the עבודה זרה avoda
zara was castrated not about that they were castrated. Totally not פשט
pshat of the פסוקים psukim but the פשט pshat of the פסוקים
psukim is that they were castrated. Anyway moving on.
Okay so now the גמרא gemara says like this. בשלמא למאן דאמר
סריסים ממש bishlama leman deamar sarisim mamash literally castrated היינו דכתיב hainu
dechsiv that's the end of the pasuk ונתתי להם יד ושם טובים
מבנים ומבנות venasasi lahem yad vashem tovim mibanim umibanos which obviously is
the whole פשט pshat of the pasuk from the beginning. אלא למאן
דאמר שנסתרסה עבודה זרה בימיהם ela leman deamar shenistarsa avoda zara bimeihem
מאי טוב מבנים ומבנות? mai tov mibanim umibanos? What do you mean
better than kids they had kids they weren't castrated. So אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak מבנים שהיו להם כבר
ומתו. mibanim shehayu lahem kvar umesu. No
maybe they had kids and they died. Okay of course that's a
very bizarre read of the whole pasuk. Anyway okay מאי שם עולם
אתן לו mai shem olam eten lo I'll give them an eternal
name אשר לא יכרת. asher lo yikares. And Rav Tanchum darshens אמר
רב תנחום דרש בר קפרא בציפורי amar Rav Tanchum darash bar Kappara
beTzippori זה ספר דניאל zeh sefer Daniel ושם עולם אשר לא יכרת
v'shem olam asher lo yikares ונתתי לו שם עולם אתן לו venasasi
lo shem olam eten lo in the singular not להם lahem right?
So that's the book of Daniel. He has the שם עולם shem
olam שנקרא על שמו shenikra al shemo that the whole book is
called for example for him and we sort of a little bit
forget חנניה Chananya, מישאל Mishael, ועזריה. v'Azarya. So now והא מכדי veha
michdi כל מילי דעזרא נחמיה בן חכליה
אמרינהו. kol milei deEzra Nechemya ben Chachalya amreinhu. Since we're talking about
the book of Daniel named after Daniel let's talk about names of
books. So the whole book of Ezra was really said by נחמיה
בן חכליה. Nechemya ben Chachalya. So why isn't it called the book
of Nechemya? So somebody should have told them that the Christians divided
it up into two books Ezra-Nechemya but according to Chazal it's only
one book and it's called Ezra. So how come Nechemya's name got
you know didn't get part of that book? So נחמיה בן חכליה
Nechemya ben Chachalya מאי טעמא לא איקרי ספרא על שמיה mai taama
lo ikri sifra al shemei
why wasn't it called after him? So אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא
amar Rabbi Yirmeya bar Abba מפני שהחזיק טובה לעצמו mipnei shehechzik tova
leatzmo because he was gave credit to himself שנאמר shenemar or he
said you know I deserve credit so if you think you deserve
credit you're not getting credit שנאמר זכרה לי אלוקי לטובה shenemar zochra
li Elokei letova
God remember this for me for good everything that I've done. So
because he said that he didn't get remembered I mean he got
remembered he's in the book but he didn't get it named after
him. דוד נמי מימר אמר David nami meimar amar what do you
mean? David also said just like that זכרני השם ברצון עמך פקדני
בישועתך zochreini Hashem birtzon amecha pakdeini bishuasecha God
remember me you know visit me with your with your salvation. דוד
רחמי הוא דקבעי David rachamei hu dekabaei David wasn't saying I deserve
it God I demand you remember me he was praying. Now how
do we know he was praying? What's different in this pasuk? So
one could say בישועתך פקדני bishuasecha pakdeini פקדני pakdeini is not like
I want my name up in the highlights פקדני pakdeini is I
want you God to answer my prayers and ישועתך yeshuasecha is your
salvation. So the end of the pasuk makes it much clearer that
it's a prayer of for help it's not I demand to be
remembered. You know and number two I would also say the difference
between זכרה לי zochra li and זכרני. zochreini. זכרני zochreini means remember
me please remember me. is different than than remember the following accomplishments
in my for me, like remember this in my remember what I
have done. I remember what I have done as you want credit
for what you've done. Okay so there is a difference.
What about the book named David?
Well that's true, but תהלים Tehillim is the ספרי sifrei is you
know like is but you're right, it's not the book is named
after. But anyway okay so בזוסיף משום דספר בגנותן של ראשונים. Bezosyf
mishum desipar bignusan shel rishonim.
It's not because he said זכרה לי, Zachrah li, it's because he
said bad things about the earlier generations. שנאמר והפחות הראשונים אשר היו
לפני הכבידו על העם ויקחו מהם בלחם ויין אחר כסף שקלים ארבעים.
Shene'emar vehapachot harishonim asher hayu lefanai hichbidu al ha'am vayikchu mehem belechem
vayein achar kesef shekalim arbaim.
So he was complaining about the previous leaders of the people, נחמיה.
Nechemia. So because he was complaining about the previous leaders, that's why
he did not get remembered. Okay, don't bad mouth your predecessors. ואף
על דניאל שקדמו ממנו סיפר. Ve'af al Daniel shekadmu mimenu siper. And
even by דניאל Daniel he was disparaged. ומנלן דגדול ממנו? Veminan degadol
mimenu? Where do we know that דניאל Daniel was greater than נחמיה?
Nechemia? דכתיב וראיתי אני דניאל לבדי את המראה והאנשים אשר היו עמי
לא ראו את המראה
אבל חרדה גדולה נפלה עליהם ויברחו בהחבא. Dichtiv vera'iti ani Daniel levadi
et hamar'eh veha'anashim asher hayu imi lo ra'u et hamar'eh aval charadah
gedolah naflah aleihem vayivrachu behachavei.
And they ran away and hiding. והאנשים אשר היו עמי לא ראו
את המראה. Veha'anashim asher hayu imi lo ra'u et hamar'eh. And they
didn't see. ומאן ניהו האנשים? Uman ni'u ha'anashim? And who were they?
So אמר רבי ירמיה ואיתימא רבי חייא בר אבא זה חגי זכריה
ומלאכי. Amar Rabi Yirmeyah ve'itma Rabi Chiya bar Abba zeh Chagai Zechariah
uMalachi.
That was חגי, Chagai, זכריה, Zechariah, and מלאכי, Malachi, those נביאים Nevi'im
that were with דניאל. Daniel. Okay so so so he was better
than them, I guess I assume we then that he's also therefore
better than than נחמיה. Nechemia.
One minute. They're next.
Right. Right, I know I know but I'm just saying but no
but he was saying that נחמיה Nechemia was disparaging the previous generations
including דניאל Daniel who was greater than them. Okay. Yeah that's what
רשי Rashi says. Since he was greater than
חגי זכריה ומלאכי Chagai Zechariah uMalachi who were the נביאים Nevi'im at
the time of נחמיה, Nechemia, clearly he was greater than נחמיה. Nechemia.
Okay now the גמרא Gemara says אינהו עדיפי מיניה ואיהו עדיף מינייהו.
Inhu adifi minei ve'ihu adif minaihu.
Now in the one way those נביאים Nevi'im were greater than דניאל,
Daniel, but in another way he was greater than them. רשי Rashi
by the way says that this whole next passage of the גמרא
Gemara is just lifted from מגילה Megillah and it probably doesn't belong
here, like maybe it was just anyway. So look at רשי. Rashi.
איידי Aidi top רשי: Rashi: איידי דגררא בעלמא קתני הכא ומילתא אגב
אורחיה וברוב ספרים אינה כתובה. Aidi d'grara be'alma katani hacha umilta agav
urchu uverov sefarim einah kesuvah. So
this that's interesting acknowledging that there are different manuscripts here and that
this passage might not be here. Anyway. He is greater they were
greater than him and he was greater than them. Top of צדיק
דלת עמוד א. Tsadik Daled Amud Aleph. אינהו עדיפי מיניה, Inhu adifi
minei, they were greater than they.
דאינהו נביאי ואיהו לאו נביא. De'inhu Nevi'ei ve'ihu lo Navi. They were
prophets right? They had a direct communication from God. ואיהו עדיף מינייהו,
Ve'ihu adif minaihu, he was greater than them, דאיהו חזא ואינהו לא
חזו. De'ihu chaza ve'inhu lo chazu. He had a vision that they
couldn't see.
Okay. וכי מאחר
דלא חזו מאי טעמא איבעתו, Vechai me'achar delo chazu mai ta'ama ivatu,
since they didn't see the vision, why did they get scared? So
it says they got scared. אף על גב דאינהו לא חזו מזלייהו
חזו. Af al gav de'inhu lo chazu mazlaihu chazu. Even though they
didn't see, their מזל mazal saw, some some you know some part
of their of their brain which would non-conscious, that's the way I'll
read it, registered that something you know supernatural was going on and
that made them fearful.
You can see a vision not be a נביא.
Navi. Correct. Yep. אמר רבינא שמע מינה האי מאן דמבעית Amar Ravina
shma mina haiman demiv'as if somebody is all of a sudden scared,
you feel this this trepidation fall on you. אף על גב דאיהו
לא חזי מזליה חזי. Af al gav de'ihu lo chazi mazlei chazi.
So and you're not seeing anything. You don't know why, oh my
god, all of a sudden I just feel so afraid. What is
that about? So your מזל, mazal, you know some sixth sense is
sensing something that you're not consciously aware of but it's something real.
So מאי תקנתיה? Mai takantei? What should you do? Because obviously it
means some maybe bad thing is about to happen. So לינשוף מדוכתיה
ארבע גרמידי. Linshof miduchtei arba garmadei.
Jump four אמות amot from where you are, like maybe some שד
shed or evil spirit is about to attack, so jump four אמות.
amot. Don't walk, jump. אינמי ליקרי קריאת שמע Inami likri krias shema
or say שמע Shema that'll protect you. ואי קאי במקום הטינופת Ve'ei
ka'ei bemakom hatinofet if you're in a filthy place and you can't
say שמע Shema you're in the bathroom or something. לימא הכי Leima
hachi say this: עיזא דבי טבחא שמינא מינאי. Iza debei tavcha shamina
minai. You know the the the goats of the of the slaughterhouse
are fatter than me. You know שדים sheidim if you want a
nice meal don't look at me go to the go to the
slaughterhouse. Okay. Now
back to fine that was a little digression.
למרבה המשרה ולשלום אין קץ.
Lemarbeh
hamisrah uleshalom ein ketz.
Okay so now we're back to talking about sort of משיח Mashiach
issues. Now we're going to so let's take a look. For
the abundancy of the dominion and for peace there is no ending.
So it sort of sounds like a like a prophecy of messianic
times right? There'll be dominion and there'll be peace. אמר רב תנחום,
Amar Rav Tanchum, דרש בר קפרא בציפורי, darash Bar Kappara b'Tzipori, מפני
מה מם שבאמצע תיבה פתוח? mipnei ma mem sheb'emtza teivah patuach? Normally
a מם mem is in the middle of a, is an open
מם, mem, is a middle
מם. mem. וזה סתום V'zeh satum in the book of ישעיהו Yeshayahu
where the word למרבה lemarbe is written, the מם mem is a
square מם. mem. It's a מם סופית. mem sofit. Why is that?
ביקש הקדוש ברוך הוא לעשות חזקיהו משיח. Bikesh Hakadosh Baruch Hu la'asos
Chizkiyahu Mashiach. This is talking about חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and about the whole
thing issue with סנחריב Sancherev when סנחריב, Sancherev, the downfall of סנחריב,
Sancherev, and חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was like deserving to then become the משיח.
Mashiach. Okay, there would never have been, we'd never have gone into
exile. וסנחריב גוג ומגוג VeSancherev Gog u'Magog and to have turned the
whole war of סנחריב Sancherev into גוג ומגוג, Gog u'Magog, the war
of גוג ומגוג. Gog u'Magog. So אמרה מדת הדין, amrah midas hadin,
I love by the way though, I guess we need to pause
for a moment that the idea is like there's this like category,
משיח Mashiach and גוג ומגוג, Gog u'Magog, and like we'll see how
history plays out. You know, like oh, okay, there was this whole
thing with חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and סנחריב Sancherev and it's like oh, well
let's turn that into משיח Mashiach and גוג ומגוג. Gog u'Magog. Like
you know, it's not like, it's you know, there's an interesting question
like fitting in with the רמב"ם Rambam's idea, right, how much is
this like a natural thing, right, and then you know, certain historical
events could turn into that. You know, and how much is it
like God has this משיח Mashiach in mind and this גוג ומגוג
Gog u'Magog in mind and God is going to make this happen
like you know, top down. Right? So this is almost like bottom
up. This was the war that happened. Oh look, this will be
the משיח Mashiach and גוג ומגוג Gog u'Magog now, it'll be the
time. Okay? So,
אמרה מדת הדין לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amrah midas hadin lifnei Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, מה דוד מלך ישראל
שאמר כמה שירות ותשבחות לפניך לא עשיתו משיח, ma Dovid melech Yisrael
she'amar kama shiros v'sishbachos lefanecha lo asiso Mashiach, דוד, Dovid, you know,
he made, he sang all of ספר תהלים Sefer Tehillim and you
never made him into משיח. Mashiach. חזקיה שעשית כל הנסים הללו ולא
אמר שירה לפניך, Chizkiyahu she'asisa kol hanissim ha'elu v'lo amar shirah lefanecha,
and he did all these miracles for him with סנחריב Sancherev and
he did not recognize it through
שירה, shirah, תעשהו משיח, ta'asehu Mashiach, you're going to make him the
משיח? Mashiach? Then that's, I always find this, it's a very, you
know, a fascinating מדרש. Midrash. חזקיהו Chizkiyahu would have been the משיח,
Mashiach, right, but he didn't sing שירה. shirah. So like, you know,
what does that mean? Like first of all, like how does this
fit in with the idea of like do we need a righteous
generation to be the משיח? Mashiach? Like the generation חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was
righteous, the generation was not so righteous in that time.
Right, like what is the idea of משיח, Mashiach, is it like
the end of history when we get to a certain level, when
we merit a certain level, when we've brought society to a certain
level? Like none of that was appropriate. It's just enough to have
a righteous king, like you know, and and then why is singing
שירה shirah like the focus? I mean of course you say oh
שירה shirah means you recognize God, you see יד ה', Yad Hashem,
but still like you know I this needs more unpacking. Like what
is this all about here? That a, why was he ראוי ra'uy
to be the משיח Mashiach and b, why was שירה shirah the
reason enough to not make that happen? Like what's going to determine
whether this is the end of history or not is whether חזקיהו
Chizkiyahu sang שירה. shirah. You know?
So, חזקיה שעשית כל הנסים הללו ולא אמר שירה לפניך תעשהו משיח?
Chizkiyahu she'asisa kol hanissim ha'elu v'lo amar shirah lefanecha ta'asehu Mashiach? לכך
נסתתם. L'kach nistaseim. Therefore the מם mem was you know it was
sealed, was silenced. Either רש"י Rashi says חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was silenced, he
didn't sing שירה, shirah, God's desire to make him the משיח Mashiach
was silenced, okay. מיד פתחה ארץ ואמרה לפניו. Miyad patchah aretz v'amrah
lefanecha. So then the landscape came to try to defend חזקיהו Chizkiyahu
or to bring משיח Mashiach and said, רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel
Olam, אני אומרת לפניך, ani omeres lefanecha, don't worry, I'll sing שירה,
shirah, I'll take it on תחת צדיק זה, tachas tzadik zeh, in
his stead. ועשהו משיח, V'asehu Mashiach, I still want you to make
him into the משיח. Mashiach. פתחה ואמרה שירה לפניו שנאמר מכנף הארץ
זמירות שמענו. Patchah v'amrah shirah lefanecha shene'emar mikanaf ha'aretz zmiros shamanu. From
the edge of the earth we have heard songs. So actually the
earth itself sang out to God. צבי לצדיק, Tzvi latzadik, glory to
the righteous. So this was done on behalf of the righteous, on
behalf of חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. Okay. אמר, Amar, so now that sounds like
that would have been good. So it's not just that חזקיהו'ס Chizkiyahu's
shortcoming, it's almost like the world needed שירה. shirah. If you want
to bring משיח, Mashiach, then you have to sort of recognize, it's
you know, the world has to be able to recognize God's hand
in everything that has just happened. Okay, so at least that works
a little better, it's not just about חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu.
אמר שר העולם לפניו. Amar sar ha'olam lefanecha. Yeah, רש"י Rashi says
it's some angel that runs the I guess day-to-day affairs of the
world, okay. Not God. Okay, some angel, you didn't know there was
an angel running the day-to-day affairs, did you? אמר שר העולם לפניו
רבונו של עולם צביונו עשה לצדיק זה. Amar sar ha'olam lefanecha Ribono
Shel Olam tzevyono aseh latzadik zeh. צביונו Tzevyono means maybe you know,
do the desire of this צדיק, tzadik, now that שירה shirah has
been sung, you should make him into the משיח. Mashiach. אוי, Oi,
so so, יצאה בת קול ואמרה, yatza bas kol v'amrah, then a
בת קול, bas kol, so many different sort of figures are getting
into this conversation, came out and said, רזי לי רזי לי, razi
li razi li, no the secret is with me, the secret is
with me. Like it's not just about the שירה, shirah, guys. Like
for whatever reason, I'm not bringing the משיח Mashiach now, it's not
yet time to bring the משיח, Mashiach, okay. Very nice he said
שירה, shirah, still no משיח. Mashiach. All right. אמר נביא, Amar navi,
אוי לי אוי לי עד מתי עד מתי. oy li oy li
ad masai ad masai. So then the נביא navi said, and which
נביא navi are we talking about, I don't know, ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, woe
to me, oh my god, so like if משיח Mashiach isn't coming
even though it was חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and the downfall of סנחריב Sancheriv
and שירה Shira was said and God is still saying, no, I
have I have my own reasons why I'm not bringing משיח. Mashiach.
So when will the משיח Mashiach come? So יצתה בת קול ואמרה
yatza bas kol ve'amrah בוגדים בגדו ובגד
בגדו, bogdim bogdu uvoged bogdu, בוגדים בגדו. bogdim bogdu. So what does
that mean? That means like you know the rebellious have rebelled or
whatever. So ואמר רבא ואיתימא רב יצחק v'amar Rava v'isema Rav Yitzchak
עד דאתו בזוזי ובזוזי דבזוזי
בוזים בגדו בגדו, ad d'asu bezuzai v'bezuzai d'bezuzai bozim bogdu bogdu, he
reads it with a זין, zayin, until those the despoilers and the
despoilers of despoilers come meaning until ישראל, Yisrael, the way רש״י Rashi
reads it, suffers greatly through the through the you know through the
foreign nations. Only after like a מצב matzav of גוג ומגוג, Gog
u'Magog, the part of the reason that סנחריב Sancheriv couldn't be גוג
ומגוג Gog u'Magog is גוג ומגוג Gog u'Magog is not supposed to
be like like the you know the entire Judean people got completely
scot-free out of that. They didn't suffer, right? The wars of גוג
ומגוג Gog u'Magog are supposed to be wars of tremendous anguish and
suffering and so on. So the גמרא Gemara says for whatever reason
משיח Mashiach can't come until a terrible period of anguish and suffering.
Okay. משא דומה אלי קרא משעיר שומר מה מלילה שומר מה מליל.
massa Dumah elai korei mi'Seir shomer mah mi'laylah shomer mah mi'leil. א
משא, a massa, א משא a massa like a prophecy of דומה
Dumah calls out to me from שעיר: Seir: watcher what of night,
what what watcher of night? So what does that mean? אמר רבי
יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan אותו מלאך הממונה על הרוחות oso malach hamumuneh
al haruchos the angel that is supervises the, this does not mean
sometimes רוחות ruchos in the context of angels, just means literally winds,
the wind in the world, but here it means the souls, the
angel who is in charge of the souls,
דומה שמו Dumah shemo his name is דומה. Dumah. So now נתקבצו
כל הרוחות אצל דומה.
nis'kabsu kol haruchos eitzel
Dumah. אמרו
לו amru lo so all these souls, maybe the souls, now I
don't know means the souls that are not yet born or the
souls of people who have died and are waiting to be resurrected.
Would make more sense in the context to say the latter. So
all the souls came to דומה. Dumah. אמרו לו amru lo they
said to him: שומר מה מלילה שומר מה מליל. shomer mah mi'laylah
shomer mah mi'leil. What is the watcher or what are you of
night, meaning night is the exile? You know, what are you waiting
for, like how long are you going to be super watching over
the night, when is the משיח Mashiach going to come? אמר, amar,
אמר שומר, amar shomer, so the פסוק pasuk says אתא בוקר, asah
voker, God says, don't worry, morning will come, משיח Mashiach will come,
וגם לילה, v'gam lailah, but all there has to be night before
morning. אם תבעיון בעיו im tiv'ayun be'ayu if you want it to
come, pray for it. Okay, so that's the way רש״י Rashi reads
it. שובו אתיו shuvu asayu return and come which רש״י Rashi means
do תשובה tshuvah and then it'll come. Okay, so it's actually I
think it's quite nice, you know, with all this talking about משיח
Mashiach and עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba ונהנין מזיו השכינה v'nehenin miziv hashchina
etc. etc. Now we're talking about like longing for the משיח, Mashiach,
right? I mean it's sort of doing it, you know, talking about
the spirit and דומה Dumah and חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and the lamb, but
fine, when is it going to come? What do we have to
do, you know? So here it's like, don't worry, have faith it
will come, but it's going to be a long period of night
and you have to work for it.
But then I always thought that like you know אתא לילה וגם
בוקר asah lailah v'gam voker meaning like you know you got to
go through that whole period of night and then have morning. But
this saying morning then night.
Right. רש״י Rashi reads it in the reverse, I don't know what
to tell you. Okay, they want, okay. תניא משום רבי פפיאס גנאי
הוא לחזקיהו וסיעתו שלא אמרו שירה. tanya mishum Rabbi Pappias gnai hu
l'Chizkiyahu v'siyaso shelo amru shira. Back to him not singing שירה shira
moving a little bit off from the משיח Mashiach question. You know,
it was a גנאי, gnai, it was a what's the word, a
how they translate גנאי, gnai, a like a gnai is usually embarrassment,
embarrass, anyway, embarrassment, something, disgrace.
Disgrace, better, discredit or disgrace, that's better. Okay, it was a disgrace
to חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and his his whole like group, it wasn't just
him. What about all of, you know, everybody there that was with
him, you know, why weren't they singing שירה? shira? עד שפתחה הארץ
ואמרה שירה, ad shepatcha ha'aretz v'amra shira, they had to wait for
the land to do it, שנאמר מכנף הארץ זמירות שמענו צבי לצדיק.
shene'emar mikanfaf ha'aretz zmiros shamanu tzevi latzadik. יוסף בדבר זה אומר Yosef
bidvar zeh omer similarly ויאמר יתרו ברוך השם אשר הציל אתכם. vayomer
Yisro baruch Hashem asher hitzil eschem.
Blessed is God who saved you. תניא משום רבי פפיאס גנאי הוא
למשה וששים ריבוא tanya mishum Rabbi Pappias gnai hu l'Moshe v'shishim ribo
משה Moshe and the six hundred thousand שלא אמרו ברוך. shelo amru
baruch. Now they did sing שירה, shira, but they didn't say ברוך.
baruch. They didn't say blessed, okay, why did they have to,
why did it have to be יתרו Yisro that wasn't, I mean
ברוך baruch is the staple of every single one of our, you
know, it's a ברכה, bracha, it's the staple of our sort of
ritual way of praising God.
I don't know, עד שבא יתרו ואמר ברוך השם.
ad
sheba Yisro v'amar baruch Hashem.
Why did, you
know, so shame on you, you had to, it had to be
יתרו Yisro had to say it before you said it. Okay, now
now that we're talking about that, ויחד יתרו, vayichad Yisro, יתרו Yisro
rejoiced. רב ושמואל, Rav v'Shmuel, רב אמר שהעביר חרב חדה על בשרו,
Rav amar shehe'evir cherev chada al besaro,
ויחד vayichad sharp, he put a sharp sword to his flesh, meaning
he circumcised himself. ושמואל אמר שנעשה חידודין חידודין כל בשרו, Shmuel amar
shena'asa chidudin chidudin kol besaro, no, his flesh sort of became like
goosebumps, right, כל בשרו. kol besaro. Okay, why? So you could say
out of joy,
but אמר רב היינו דאמרי אינשי amar Rav hayinu d'amri inshi this
is what people say, גיורא עד עשרה דרי לא תבזי ארמאה קמיה
giura ad asara daray lo tivzei Armaya kamei do not disparage. and
praising God and said ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, he still felt a
certain, you know,
association, connection to these Egyptians and part of him felt terrible that
they were all they still weren't the complete other, you know, which
is like, you know, they were still somebody you feel, I mean,
so like the גמרא, Gemara, right? The גמרא Gemara says that the
מלאכים Malachim wanted to say שירה, shira, and God said מעשי ידי,
Ma'asei Yadai, right? So, you know, so he so they still felt
some association with them, closeness to them.
Okay. לכן ישלח האדון השם צבאות במשמניו רזון. Lochen yeshalach Adon Hashem
Tzevaos b'mishmanav razon. Therefore God will send to his fat ones leanness.
So what does that mean?
מאי במשמניו רזון? Mai b'mishmanav razon? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, יבוא חזקיה שיש לו שמונה, yavo Chizkiyahu sheyesh lo shmoneh,
so it's playing a word on במשמניו b'mishmanav of שמונה. shmoneh. Let
חזקיה Chizkiyahu come, that he has שמונה שמות, shmoneh shemos, eight, eight
names, ויפרע מסנחריב v'yipara miSancheriv and let him take punish, you know,
accounting from סנחריב, Sancheriv, you know, punishment of סנחריב Sancheriv שיש לו
שמונה שמות, sheyesh lo shmoneh shemos, that he has eight names. So
the eight ones,
חזקיה Chizkiyahu and סנחריב, Sancheriv, רזון, razon, leanness, in the sense that
סנחריב Sancheriv will be punished. Okay. Now,
חזקיה דכתיב, Chizkiyahu deksiv, so here are the eight names of חזקיה.
Chizkiyahu. כי ילד יולד לנו בן ניתן לנו ותהי המשרה על שכמו,
Ki yeled yulad lanu ben nitan lanu vatehi hamisrah al shichmo, the
government you know will be on his on his shoulders, ויקרא שמו,
vayikra shemo, his name will be called פלא Pele one, יועץ Yoetz
two, אל גיבור, El Gibbor, I think אל El is three, גיבור
Gibbor is four, אביעד Aviad is five, שר שלום Sar Shalom is
six. So how do we get eight?
I don't I lost track. What?
Oh you just break the אל גיבור. El Gibbor.
אבי, Avi,
yeah, let's see. פלא Pele one, יועץ Yoetz two, אל, El, right,
every every word is different. אל, El, גיבור, Gibbor, אבי, עד, Avi
Ad, שר, Sar, שלום. Shalom. Yeah, אבי Avi, עד, Ad, yeah, I
don't know, each each word is different. והאיכא חזקיה, V'haika Chizkiyahu, but
what do you mean? He's got nine names? חזקיה Chizkiyahu is his
name. No, שחזקו יה, shechizko Yah,
that's not his proper name. That's just a descriptive name, as if
the other things weren't descriptive. Okay. The other things were proper names,
that's just descriptive. God strengthened him. דבר אחר, Davar acher, חזקיה שחיזק
את ישראל לאביהם שבשמים. Chizkiyahu shechizak es Yisrael l'avihem shebashamayim. He strengthened
Israel's relationship with יה, Yah, with God. Okay, but they're descriptive, they're
not proper names. סנחריב דכתיב, Sancheriv deksiv, סנחריב, Sancheriv, it says תגלת
Tiglath one, פלאסר Pileser two, פלנאסר Pulneser three, שלמנאסר Shalmaneser four, פול
Pul five, סרגון Sargon six,
אסנפר Asnappar seven, רבא, Rabba, oh I guess תגלת פלאסר Tiglath Pileser
they're reading as one, so we're up to six, רבא Rabba seven,
ויקירא v'yakira
eight. Okay, רבא ויקירא Rabba v'yakira means like great and and honorable.
But we're counting them as names. והאיכא סנחריב, V'haika Sancheriv, what do
you mean? He's got another name? סנחריב. Sancheriv. No, that's just descriptive.
ששיחתו ריב, sheshichaso riv, it means he always is, I know.
Okay. He's always talking contentiously, סנ, san,
שיחה, shicha, ריב. riv. Okay. דבר אחר שסח וניחר, Davar acher shesach
v'nichar,
so סנ, san, נחר, nichar, he he spoke and he like snorted
דברים כלפי מעלה devarim klapei ma'alah against God. He blasphemed God. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, מפני מה זכה אותו רשע לקרות אסנפר
רבא ויקירא? mipnei mah zachah oso rasha likros Asnappar Rabba v'yakira? Why
was he called אסנפר Asnappar the great and the glorious one? מפני
שלא סיפר בגנותה של ארץ ישראל mipnei shelo siper bignushah shel Eretz
Yisrael because with all the bad that he did, he didn't say
anything bad about the land of Israel. שנאמר עד בואי ולקחתי אתכם
אל ארץ כארצכם. shene'emar ad bo'i v'lakachti eschem el eretz k'artzechem. I
will take you to a land like your land. He didn't say
better than your land. So he didn't praise Israel either, right? He
said like your land. But that verse means it's an acknowledgment that
you're in a good land, but don't worry, I'll take you to
another good one as well. So he didn't disparage it. Okay. רב
ושמואל, Rav uShmuel, חד אמר מלך פיקח היה, chad amar melech pike'ach
hayah, he was smart when he said that, וחד אמר מלך טיפש
היה, v'chad amar melech tipesh hayah, he was stupid. Yeah. למאן דאמר
מלך פיקח היה, L'man d'amar melech pike'ach hayah, אי אמינא להו דטבא
מארעכו, ei amina lehu d'tava m'archu, why didn't he say I'll take
you to a land better than your land? Because if he had
said that, אמרו קא משקרת, amru ka meshakres, hey, you're a liar!
There could be nothing better than the land of Israel. Okay, ולמאן
דאמר מלך טיפש היה, u'l'man d'amar melech tipesh hayah, he was stupid,
אם כן, im ken, so if all you're saying is I'll take
you to a land just as good, מאי רבותיה? mai revusei? So
what what so what so why should we leave if it's only
going to be just as good as it is here?
You'll be killed.
I understand. Okay. והיכא אגלי? V'heicha iglei? Now where were the ten
tribes exiled to? מר זוטרא אמר לאפריקי, Mar Zutra amar l'Afriki, into
Africa. ורב דניאל אמר, v'Rav Daniel amar, להרי סלוג, l'harei Selug, I
have no idea where the mountains of Selug are. אבל ישראל, Aval
Yisrael, so that's סנחריב, Sancheriv, he did not speak about the bad
of land, but the Israelites סיפרו בגנותה של ארץ ישראל, siperu bignushah
shel Eretz Yisrael, they did speak disparagingly of the land. כי מטו
שוש, Ki matu Shosh, when they came to the place called שוש
Shosh or, I guess, אמרו שויא כי ארען, amru shavya ki aran,
play on words, שוש, Shosh, שויא, shavya, שויא כי ארען, shavya ki
aran, oh, this is just as good as Israel. Great. Okay, maybe
it's also sort of explaining why they remained in exile and why
they got lost. They were happy where they were moved to. כי
מטו עלמין, Ki matu Almin,
when they came to a place called עלמין, Almin, אמרו כעלמין, amru
k'almin, it's just like... our past world, our past lives. כי מטו
שוש תרי, Ki matu Shosh Trei, there was a place called שוש
תרי, Shosh Trei, אמרו, amru, you know what? חד תרי, a-trei, this
is twice as good as where we used to be living. Okay,
so and so that's why the you know so that's they were
worse than סנחריב Sancheirev in that respect. Okay, ותחת כבודו יקד יקוד
כיקוד אש, V'tachas k'vodo yekad yekod kiykod esh, under his glory like
a burning fire, like the fire of a like the like the
like a fire flagration whatever. What does that mean? אמר רב יוחנן
Amar Rav Yochanan תחת כבודו ולא כבודו ממש, Tachas k'vodo v'lo k'vodo
mamash, under his כבוד, kavod, but כבוד kavod isn't literal. רש"י Rashi
says כבודו kavodo literally would assume body and under his כבודו kavodo
would be the soul in the body. And he's saying don't read
כבודו kavodo literal, כבודו kavodo is metaphor. So what does כבודו kavodo
refer to if it's metaphoric? כי הא דרבי יוחנן Ki ha d'Rabbi
Yochanan קרי ליה למאני מכבדותי, kari lei l'mani machbadusai, he called his
clothes the things that honor me. So under
his under his clothes it'll be burnt, means his body will be
burnt beneath his clothes. This is the end of the פסוק pasuk
of God will send במשמניו רזון. b'mishmanav razon. So God will send
with his eight ones is a way of treating leanness. חזקיה Chizkiyah
is going to punish סנחריב Sancheirev and they'll be burnt. סנחריב Sancheirev
will be burnt. So this is reading the bodies will be burnt.
Okay. Under the כבודו, kavodo, under the clothes, the bodies will be
burnt. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer תחת כבודו ממש, tachas k'vodo
mamash, כבודו kavodo refers to the bodies. So under the bodies will
be burnt means the souls will be burnt. Okay. כשרפת בני אהרן,
Kishreifat bnei Aharon, now להלן, l'halan, like the children of אהרן, Aharon,
שרפת נשמה וגוף קיים, sreifas neshama v'guf kayam, the soul is burnt
and the body's around, אף כאן שרפת נשמה וגוף קיים. af kan
sreifas neshama v'guf kayam. Okay. תני, Tani, back to סנחריב, Sancheirev, משמיה
דרבי יהושע בן קרחה, mishmei d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, פרעה שחירף בעצמו,
Paroh she-cheiref b'atzmo, פרעה Paroh cursed out God בעצמו. be-atzmo. So נפרע
הקדוש ברוך הוא ממנו בעצמו. nifra ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu mimenu be-atzmo. Alright,
that's a horrific thing, but at least it's even worse to like
say it's not you know like we're going to see סנחריב Sancheirev
did it through a messenger. Through a messenger it's not even worth
my time, I'll have a messenger curse out God. So okay, at
least פרעה Paroh did it on his own. God at least showed
him the respect of punishing of God directly punishing פרעה. Paroh. Okay.
סנחריב שחירף על ידי מלאך Sancheirev she-cheiref al yedei malach בעצם על
ידי שליח, al yedei shaliach, סנחריב Sancheirev that did it through a
messenger, נפרע הקדוש ברוך הוא ממנו על ידי שליח. nifra ha-Kadosh Baruch
Hu mimenu al yedei shaliach. God punished him through a שליח. shaliach.
פרעה דכתיב ביה Paroh d'chsiv bei מי ה' אשר אשמע בקולו, Mi
Hashem asher eshma b'kolo, why should I listen to God? נפרע הקדוש
ברוך הוא ממנו בעצמו דכתיב Nifra ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu mimenu be-atzmo d'chsiv
וינער ה' את מצרים, Vayanar Hashem es Mitzrayim, God turned up
Egypt בתוך הים. besoch ha-yam. וכתיב דרכת בים סוסיך, U'chsiv darachta ba-yam
susecha, you trampled in the through the sea with your horses fine.
סנחריב דכתיב ביד מלאכיך חרפת ה', Sancheirev d'chsiv b'yad malachecha cheirafta Hashem,
through your messengers you blasphemed God, so נפרע הקדוש ברוך הוא ממנו
על ידי שליח. nifra ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu mimenu al yedei shaliach. God
punished him through a שליח. shaliach. דכתיב D'chsiv ויצא מלאך ה' ויך
במחנה אשור, vayeitzei malach Hashem vayach b'machaneh Ashur, the angel of God
came and smote in the camp of אשור Ashur מאה ושמונים וחמשה
אלף. me'ah u'shmonim v'chamishah elef. רבי חנינא בר פפא רמי, Rabbi Chanina
bar Papa rami, he showed a contradiction. כתיב Ksiv מרום קיצו, marom
kitzo, the God's you know the high place of whatever.
וכתיב U'chsiv מלון קיצו, melon kitzo, where God's like the inn, the
place God rests. So אמר אותו רשע, amar oso rasha, this is
the curse of God.
בתחלה אחריב דירה של מטה, Betichala achriv dirah shel mata, so this
was quoting סנחריב. Sancheirev. First he said מרום קיצו, marom kitzo, somehow
that refers to you know
the בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. I will destroy where God lives down
here. ואחר כך אחריב דירה של מעלה. V'achar kach achriv dirah shel
ma'ala. Then I'll get to מלון קיצו melon kitzo where He's really
sleeping, where He really resides up in heaven. אמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi מאי דכתיב mai d'chsiv אתה המבלעדי
ה' עליתי על המקום הזה להשחיתו? atah hamibaledei Hashem alisiy al ha-makom
ha-zeh l'hashchiso? This is again סנחריב Sancheirev talking and so saying that
he's going to wipe out. He says look, you know God must
be helping me. Until now look how successful I've been. I've exiled
the ten tribes. Was it without God that I was able to
come up upon this place to destroy it?
ה' אמר אלי Hashem amar elai עלה אל הארץ הזאת והשחיתה, aleh
el ha-aretz ha-zos v'hashchisah, to destroy it. This is what סנחריב Sancheirev
is saying. Okay, מאי היא? mai hi? So what does it mean
God is telling me? So the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk
is because my success is my way of seeing that God is
telling me this. But here the גמרא Gemara is going to say
something a little bit more. דשמע לנביא Deshama l'navi דקאמר d'ka'amar יען
כי מאס העם הזה את מי השלוח ההולכים לאט, ya'an ki ma'as
ha-am ha-zeh es mei ha-Shiloach ha-holchim l'at, this people has despised the
the waters of the שילוח Shiloach that go slowly
ומשוש את רצין ובן רמליהו u'mesos es Retzin u'ven Remalyahu and they
have rejoiced in רצין Retzin and בן רמליהו. ben Remalyahu. So what
does that mean? אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef אלמלא תרגומא דהאי
קרא, ilmalei targuma d'hai kra, if not for the Aramaic translation of
this
word לא הוי ידענא מאי קאמר, lo havi yadana mai ka'amar, we
wouldn't know what it was saying. Here's here's the translation: חלף דקץ
עמא הדין במלכותא דבית דוד, Chalaf d'katz ama hadein b'malchusa d'veis David,
since this people have despised the rulership of the house of David,
the kingship of the house of David, דמדבר להון בנייח, d'midaber l'hon
binayach, that treats them you know with with pleasantness with not with
harshness, with kindness, כמי שילוחא דנגדין בנייח, k'mei Shiloacha d'nagdin binayach, like
the waters of the שילוח Shiloach that you know that travel pleasantly,
ואתאיתו עלייהו ית רצין ובר רמליהו, v'iseisu aleiyehu yas Retzin u'var Remalyahu,
and they chose rather the rulership of רצין Retzin and בן רמליהו,
ben Remalyahu, so they want the kingship of the מלכי ישראל malchei
Yisrael and not מלכי יהודה, malchei Yehudah, therefore I am going to
exile them. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan מאי דכתיב mai
d'chsiv מארת ה' בבית רשע me'iras Hashem b'veis rasha ונוה צדיקים יבורך.
u'nevei tzadikkim yevorach. The curse of God is
in the house of the wicked and the and the domicile of
the righteous will be blessed. מארת ה' בבית רשע *me'erat Hashem b'veit
rasha* זה פקח בן רמליהו *zeh Pekach ben Remalyahu* שהיה אוכל מ'
סאה גוזלות בקינוח סעודה *she'hayah ochel mem se'ah gozalot b'kinuach se'uda* for
dessert he would eat forty like you know gallons worth of a
pigeons and he was still not satisfied. No matter how much he
ate he wasn't satisfied. ונוה צדיקים יבורך *v'naveh tzadikkim yevorach* that the
domicile of the righteous will be blessed זה חזקיה מלך יהודה *zeh
Chizkiyah Melech Yehudah* שהיה אוכל ליטרא ירק בסעודה *she'hayah ochel litra yerek
b'se'uda* he just had some vegetables, okay, and he was totally happy.
Okay. So anyway so because back to the point, so סנחריב *Sancherev*
heard the prophet saying these people have chosen you know רצין ובן
רמליהו *Retzin u'ven Remalyahu* ולכן הנה ה' מעלה עליהם את מי הנהר
*v'lachen hinei Hashem ma'aleh aleihem et mei hanahar* therefore this is you
know ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* prophesied this. God will bring up against you the
waters of the river העצומים והרבים את מלך אשור *ha'atzumim v'harabim et
Melech Ashur*. So ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* prophesied that the King of Assyria סנחריב
*Sancherev* would come. Okay so it was a prophecy about the ten
tribes, it wasn't a prophecy about יהודה *Yehudah*. וכתיב וחלף ביהודה שטף
ועבר *u'chtiv v'chalaf b'Yehudah shataf v'avar* this river will pass through יהודה
*Yehudah* and it will pass עד צואר יגיע *ad tzavar yagi'a* it'll
get up to the neck. Okay? So part of the prophecy included
יהודה *Yehudah*. So סנחריב *Sancherev* said, so God is telling me come
and destroy the land. Of course part of the prophecy was that
it'll get up to the neck but it won't kill them, right?
אלא מאי טעמא איענש *ela mai ta'ama i'enash*? So okay so then
why was סנחריב *Sancherev* punished? He really God was telling him. No.
נביא אעשרת שבטים אתנבי *navi a'aseret shevatim itnabi*. The prophet was prophesying
on the ten tribes. איהו יהב דעתיה אכולה *ihu yahav da'atei a'kula*
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, he wanted to get it all, he wanted even ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*, it just said up to the neck, right? But he so
that's what his sin was he took it further. בא נביא ואמר
ליה *ba navi v'amar lei* so the prophet came and said to
him, כי לא מועף לאשר מוצק לה *ki lo mu'af la'asher mutzak
lah*. What does that mean? אמר רבי אלעזר בר ברכיה *amar Rabi
Elazar bar Brachyah* אין עם זו עייף מועף *ein am zu ayef
mu'af* the people that is weary, the righteous part of the nation
Judea, okay, עייף בתורה *ayef baTorah* they are weary in the learning
of תורה *Torah*, they devote themselves to the learning of תורה *Torah*,
so they לא ימסרו *lo yimasru* so they will not be given
over ביד מי המציק לה *b'yad mi hametzik lah* to the one
who is you know besieging them. So you will not get Judea.
You got the ten tribes, you will not get יהודה *Yehudah* and
בנימין *Binyamin*. Okay מאי כהעת ראשון הקל ארץ זבולון וארץ נפתלי *mai
ka'et rishon hekal eretz Zevulun
v'eretz Naftali*? Like the first time was light on the land of
זבולון *Zevulun* and נפתלי *Naftali* והאחרון הכביד דרך הים עבר הירדן גליל
הגוים *v'ha'acharon hichbid derech hayam avar haYarden Galil haGoyim*. So what does
all that mean? לא כראשונים *lo k'rishonim* don't think ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* was
saying to סנחריב *Sancherev* you'll be like the early ones, the ten
tribes, that's זבולון *Zevulun* and נפתלי *Naftali*. Why were you successful against
them? שהקלו מעליהם עול תורה *she'hikilu me'aleihem ol Torah* because they disparaged
the yoke of the תורה *Torah*, that's הקל *hekal*, they treated it
lightly. אבל אחרונים *aval acharonim* now you're dealing with the later ones,
יהודה *Yehudah* and בנימין *Binyamin*, שהכבידו עליהם עול תורה *she'hichbidu aleihem ol
Torah* it was they treated the עול תורה *ol Torah* as weighty
וראויים הם לעשות להם נס *v'ra'uyim hem la'asot lahem nes* they are
fit to have a miracle done to them כאוברי הים *k'ovrei hayam*
that's דרך הים עבר הירדן *derech hayam avar haYarden* וכדרכי הירדן *u'ch'darchei
haYarden* like you know בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* when they passed through
the ים סוף *Yam Suf* and when they passed through the ירדן
*Yarden*, they will also have a miracle done to them. אם חוזר
בו מוטב *im chozer bo mutav* now if you סנחריב *Sancherev* you
know retreat, good, ואם לאו *v'im lav* but if not אני אעשה
לו גליל בגוים *ani e'eseh lo galil bagoyim* that's the end of
it, דרך הים עבר הירדן גליל הגוים *derech hayam avar haYarden Galil
haGoyim* I'll make you like dung among the nations. Okay so just
be one more minute. אחר הדברים והאמת האלה *acharei hadvarim v'ha'emet ha'eleh*
after these words and these truths בא סנחריב מלך אשור ויבא ביהודה
ויחן על הערים הבצורות *ba Sancherev Melech Ashur vayavo biYehudah vayichan al
he'arim habtzurot* and he laid siege to the to the walled cities
ויאמר לבקעם אליו *vayomer l'vka'am elav* and he wanted to burst through
them. היי רישנא להאי פרדשנא *hai rishnah l'hai pardashna*? This is the
gift that you give to this officer? Meaning what does it mean?
After you say אמת *emet* that you know חזקיה *Chizkiyah* was in
the right, so why does it then say, oh, after the truth
of this then סנחריב *Sancherev* laid siege? Like it sounds like סנחריב
*Sancherev* is being rewarded or something. So אחר הדברים והאמת *acharei hadvarim
v'ha'emet* here's what it means. אחר הדברים והאמת *acharei hadvarim v'ha'emet* מאי
אחר *mai achar*? אמר רבינא *amar Ravina* לאחר שקפץ הקדוש ברוך הוא
ונשבע *l'achar she'kafatz Hakadosh Baruch Hu v'nishba* after God got up and
took an oath. אי אמינא ליה לחזקיה מייתינא ליה לסנחריב ומסנא ליה
בידך *ei amina lei l'Chizkiyah
mayiteina lei l'Sancherev u'masna lei b'yadach* if I were to say to
חזקיה *Chizkiyah*, חזקיה *Chizkiyah*, you know what? I'll give you סנחריב *Sancherev*
and you'll wipe his whole nation will be wiped out. השתא אמר
לא הוא בעינא ולא ביעותיה בעינא *hashtah amar lo hu be'ina v'lo
bi'utei be'ina*. חזקיה *Chizkiyah* would say, you know what God, I'd rather
not have to go through the anguish of being besieged and the
whole process for the end result. So if I were to give
חזקיה *Chizkiyah* the offer he would turn me down. Therefore I'm not
going to give him the offer. מיד קפץ הקדוש ברוך הוא ונשבע
*miyad kafatz Hakadosh Baruch Hu v'nishba* God said forget חזקיה *Chizkiyah*, I
swear says God דמייתינא ליה *d'mayiteina lei* that I will bring סנחריב
*Sancherev* against חזקיה *Chizkiyah* in order
that סנחריב *Sancherev* should ...shatter אשור *Ashur* in my land ועל הרי
אבוסנו *Ve'al Herai Avusenu* and in my
on my mountain I will אבוסנו *Avusenu* trample him or we'll see
what that word means. וסר מעליהם עלו *Vesar Me'aleihem Ulo* the yoke
of the king of אשור *Ashur* will be removed from חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*
וסבלו מעל שכמו יסור *Vesivlo Me'al Shichmo Yasur* his burden from the
shoulders. So that's after the אמת *Emet*. The אמת *Emet* is God.
After God swore because really סנחריב *Sancheirev* could have turned around. God
wanted it to happen. After God swore because God wanted to destroy
סנחריב *Sancheirev* by the merit of חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* even if חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*
wouldn't have wanted it, then סנחריב *Sancheirev* laid siege and then the
miracle came and wiped it out. Okay let's just finish this one
thought. אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan* הקדוש ברוך הוא *HaKadosh Baruch
Hu* יבוא סנחריב וסיעתו *Yavo Sancheirev Vesi'ato* let them come ויעשה אבוס
*Veya'aseh Avus* this is the word of אבוס *Avus* let them be
made as a feeding trough לחזקיהו וסיעתו *Lichizkiyahu Vesi'ato* for חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*
and his group cause meaning the bodies will be laid on the
field and they'll be able to be eaten by the animals so
that's the word אבוסנו *Avusenu* they'll be a feeding trough. Okay. והיה
ביום ההוא *Vehaya Bayom Hahu* and on that day יסור סבלו מעל
שכמך ועלו מעל צוארך *Yasur Sivlo Me'al Shichmecha Ve'ulo Me'al Tzavarecha* the
yoke will be removed from your neck וחובל עול מפני שמן *Vechubal
Ol Mipnei Shamen* and the yoke will be destroyed because of the
oil. What does it mean because of the oil? אמר רבי יצחק
נפחא *Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha* חובל עול של סנחריב *Chubal Ol Shel
Sancheirev* the yoke of סנחריב *Sancheirev* will be destroyed מפני שמנו של
חזקיהו *Mipnei Shamno Shel Chizkiyahu* the oil of חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*. What does
that mean? שהיה דולק בבתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות *Shehaya Dolek Bevatei Knesiyot
Ubevatei Midrashot*. And now we're going to speak about the merit of
חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* which we had alluded to before, it was time for
משיח *Mashiach* should have come. His merit was that he spread תורה
*Torah* throughout the land of Israel and the oil was always burning
in the synagogues and in the study halls and that's why if
I remember before we said הם הכבידו עליהם עול תורה *Hem Hichbidu
Aleihem Ol Torah* so they took the yoke of תורה *Torah* seriously.
So this is now we're getting an image why the גמרא's *Gemara's*
thinking that the time of it should have been the Messianic times
because here it wasn't just the righteousness of חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*, people before
him had been idolatrous but through the you know הוא מחזיר העם
לטובה *Hu Machzir Ha'am Letova* right and therefore תורה *Torah* had spread
and that's being read now, they took the yoke of the תורה
*Torah* seriously. Okay so מה עשה *Ma Asa* what did he do?
נעץ חרב על פתח בית המדרש *Na'atz Cherev Al Petach Beit HaMidrash*
he took a sword by the opening of the בית המדרש *Beit
HaMidrash* I guess after everybody was in the בית מדרש *Beit Midrash*.
ואמר כל מי שאינו עוסק בתורה *Ve'amar Kol Mi She'eino Osek BaTorah*
anybody who wants to leave okay ידקר בחרב זו *Yidaker Bacherev Zu*
fine, walk out of the door you'll be struck by the you'll
be speared by the sword. Okay זו *Zu* this sword. בדקו מדן
ועד באר שבע *Badku MiDan Ve'ad Be'er Sheva* and they checked from
the north of Israel to the south ולא מצאו עם הארץ *Velo
Matzu Am Ha'aretz* nobody was ignorant. מגבת ועד אנטיפרס *Migevat Ve'ad Antipatris*
ולא מצאו תינוק ותינוקת *Velo Matzu Tinok Vetinoket* they didn't even find
a baby or child, איש ואשה *Ish Ve'isha* man or woman שלא
היו בקיאין בהלכות טומאה וטהרה *Shelo Hayu Beki'in Behilchot Tuma Vetahara* that
were not completely conversant not only with like כשרות *Kashrut* and שבת
*Shabbat* and נשים ונזיקין *Nashim Unizikin* like even the most even the
laws of טומאה וטהרה *Tuma Vetahara*. ועל אותו הדור הוא אומר *Ve'al
Oto Hador Hu Omer* by that generation it says והיה ביום ההוא
יחיה איש עגלת בקר *Vehaya Bayom Hahu Yichye Ish Egat Bakar* okay
we'll end there. Okay we'll continue obviously tomorrow but we're already a
good deal over. But the final point I want to make is
so now we're getting a much better sense why it's a Messianic
times cause you know the basic point of Messianic times for רמב״ם
*Rambam* is a king that will restore the people to do מצוות
*Mitzvot*, will spread the knowledge of God, will spread the knowledge of
תורה *Torah*. Right? So now it's not just חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*, it's ממש
*Mamash* that oh okay it's Messianic times, everybody's learning תורה *Torah*, the
knowledge of God is spreading, people are going back from their evil
ways. Right? So now to really think what it means that just
because they didn't sing שירה *Shira*, that was the one thing that
prevented it from happening, like in the end the גמרא *Gemara* says
that well it wasn't the only thing. Okay but anyway but now
at least we're getting an understanding why they imagined that חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu*
was deserving of being the משיח *Mashiach*. All right so we will
continue with this tomorrow.
Thank you for listening.